As we mentioned earlier,
正如我们之前说的
in addition to accessing individual elements one at a time,
除了逐个访问元素外
we can access subsets of NumPy arrays with slicing.
我们还可以用切片操作来访问 NumPy 数组的子集
Slicing is performed by combining indices with a colon inside the brackets.
要切片 可以在括号里填入索引 并以冒号隔开
In general, you will come across three ways of slicing.
总地来说 有三种切片方法
First, slicing from a starting index to an ending index.
第一种 从起始索引开始 到终止索引为止
Second, slicing from a starting index to the end of the array,
第二种 在这里留白 就会从起始索引开始 到数组末端为止
by leaving this blank, or slicing from the beginning of
第三种 在这里留白 就会从数组开头开始
the array to an ending index, by leaving this part blank.
到终止索引为止
In the first and third methods,
一般来说 第一种和第三种方法
the ending index is always excluded.
终止索引不在访问范围内
While here, the starting index is always included.
而这里的起始索引是在访问范围内的
NumPy arrays can be multidimensional.
NumPy 数组可以是多维的
So, when slicing, you usually have to specify a slice for each dimension of the array.
所以在切片时 一般要指定数组各维的切片位置
Let's see some examples of slicing,
我们来看一些切片例子
with a rank two array.
以秩为 2 的数组为例
Here is a four by five array that contains integers from one to 20.
这个 4 x 5 的数组包含整数 1 到 20
Let's say, you wanted to grab this subset from the array, these nine values.
假设你要从数组里提取这个子集 也就是这九个值
Here is one way we can do this.
这是一种切片方法
The part before the comma,
逗号前面的部分
specifies what indices you want to grab from the rows,
指定了提取目标行的索引
and the part after the comma specifies what indices you want to grab from the columns.
逗号后面的部分 指定了提取目标列的索引
Remember, the starting index is included and the ending index is excluded.
记住 起始索引在访问范围内 但终止索引不在
And indexing always starts with zero.
而索引一般是从 0 开始的
So, the first row is zero and the second column is one.
所以第一行索引为 0 第二行为 1
So, this grabs the rows one, two, and three.
因此 这个部分要提取的第 1、2、3 行是这些
And this part grabs the columns two, three, and four.
这个部分要提取的第 2、3、4 列是这些
Here is another way we can accomplish that same thing.
还有一种切片方法也可以实现同样的效果
Remember, if we don't include an ending index after the colon,
记住 如果冒号后没有终止索引
it will just go all the way to the last index.
切片就默认到最后一个索引为止
Let's try to grab another subset that uses these same columns,
用这些列索引 我们试着提取别的子集
but instead of the last three rows,
这次不提取后三行了
grabs the first three rows.
我们要提取前三行
This grabs this subset.
这行代码提取了这个子集
Remember, not including a starting index before
记住 不在冒号前写起始索引的话
the colon just makes it go all the way to the beginning of the array.
切片就默认从数组开头开始
So, this grabs the rows zero, one, and two.
因而提取出了第 0、1、2 行
For our next example,
再举一个例子
let's try to select all the elements in the third row.
我们要选中第三行的所有元素
If we leave both sides of the colon blank,
如果冒号两边都不填索引的话
this will just grab all the rows in the array.
切片就默认提取数组的所有行
So, X, colon, comma,
所以 x [ : , 2]
two will get all the rows in column two.
会提取第二列的所有行
So, zero, one, two it would grab this column.
0、1、2 因此会提取这一列
If we want to select all the elements in the third column but
如果我们想选中第三列的所有元素
return it in a rank two array, we can do this.
但将其返回成一个秩为 2 的数组 我们可以这么做
Notice that when we first selected all the elements in the third column this way,
注意 当我们这么选出第三列的所有元素时
the slice returned a rank one array instead of a rank two array.
切片返回了一个秩为 1 的数组 而非秩为 2 的数组
But slicing X like this,
如果像这样对 X 进行切片
in a slightly different way,
虽然只改变了一点
can get us a rank two NumPy array.
但我们就得到了一个秩为 2 的 NumPy 数组
It's important to note that when we perform slices on
注意 在对 NumPy 数组进行切片
NumPy arrays and save them into new variables,
并将其保存到新变量中时
like we did here, the data is not actually copied into the new variable.
就像这里 实际上数据并没有复制到新变量中
This is one feature that often causes confusion for beginners.
这一点总是让新手很困惑
So, we'll look into this in more detail.
所以我们来具体讲讲
In these examples, the slice of the original array X,
在这些例子中 原数组 X 的切片
is not copied into the variable Z.
并没有复制到变量 z 中
Rather, X and Z are now just two different names for the same array.
相反 X 和 z 只是同一个数组的两个不同名称
We say that slicing only creates a view of the original array.
我们说 切片是原数组的新视角
This means, if you make any changes in Z,
也就是说 你对 z 做出的任何修改
you'll also be changing the elements in X.
都会改变 X 里的元素
Let's see an example with that four by five array.
以那个 4 x 5 数组为例
We'll select the elements over here again,
我们再选中这里的元素
and assign that to the variable Z.
并将其赋给变量 z
Now, we'll change the last element in Z to 555.
现在 把 z 的最后一个元素改为 555
Now, if we print X,
此时如果输出 X
we can see that it has also been affected by this change.
我们会发现 X 也有同样的改动
If we want to create a new NumPy array that contains a copy of the values in the slice,
要新建 NumPy 数组来存放切片值副本
we need to use NumPy's Copy function.
就用 NumPy 的函数 copy
This function can also be used as a method,
这个函数也可以当方法用
as we saw before with the reshape function.
就像之前的函数 reshape 一样
Let's repeat this example with the copy command.
还是用这个例子 我们来看看 copy 命令
Here's X again, we'll create a copy of the same slice using the copy function.
还是这个数组 X 我们用函数 copy 来为这个切片创建一个副本
We can also use Copy as a method like this.
我们还可以像这样把 copy 当方法用
If we change the last element in Z to 555,
再把 z 的最后一个元素改为 555
we can see that X has not been changed.
这次 X 就没有变化了
By using the Copy command,
使用 copy 命令
we are creating a new NumPy array,
我们就可以新建
that is completely independent of the original.
完全独立于原数组的NumPy 数组了
It's often useful to use an array as indices to make slices,
把数组当索引用
select, or change elements in another NumPy array.
就能很方便地对别的 NumPy 数组进行切片、选择及元素更改等操作了
Let's see some examples.
来看些例子
Let's create a rank one array that will serve as indices to select elements from X.
我们来创建一个秩为 1 的数组 以其为索引 对 X 的元素进行选择
We'll use this indices NumPy array to select the second and fourth row of X.
我们可以用这个 NumPy 索引数组来选择 X 的第二和第四行
Now, we'll use the same array to select the second and fourth column of X.
也可以用这个数组来选择 X 的第二和第四列
NumPy also offers built-in functions to select specific elements within NumPy arrays.
NumPy 还提供了一些内置函数 用于选择 NumPy 数组里的特定元素
For example, NumPy's diag function can extract elements along the diagonal of an array.
比如 NumPy 的函数 diag 可以提取数组对角线上的元素
Remember, X was this.
记住 X 是这个
We can also print the elements above the main diagonal of X by setting a parameter,
我们还可以输出在 X 主对角线上方的元素
K equal to one.
只需将参数 k 设为 1 即可
This grabs the elements one, seven,13, and 19.
这样 diag 就会提取元素 1、7、13 和 19 了
If K is a negative number,
如果 k 为负值
this will grab the values below the main diagonal, five,11, and 17.
那 diag 就会提取主对角线下方的数值 即 5、11 和 17
By default, K is zero,
k 默认为 0
which is why it gets the main diagonal.
因此默认提取的是主对角线上的元素
It's also often useful to extract only the unique elements in a NumPy array.
仅提取 NumPy 数组里独一无二的元素也是常用操作
We can find the unique elements in an array by using NumPy's Unique function.
我们可以用 NumPy 函数 unique 来找出数组独一无二的元素
Here's a three by three array with repeated values.
这个 3 x 3 数组里有重复的值
We can see the unique values like this.
我们可以像这样找出数组里独一无二的值